Preliminary Guide to the [Martin K. Gordon Collection], 1955-1976 MS2097
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Martin K. Gordon collection
1967-1976
1969-1971
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2097
1.75 Linear Feet
Scope and Contents
This collection is made up of the research files of Martin K. Gordon for the hearings on Riots, Civil and Criminal Disorders of the Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations of the Committee on Government Operations. The committee was investigating the protests and civil unrest that developed in the late 1960s and early 1970s. The collection includes articles from periodicals and journals, congressional committee transcripts and bibliographic materials. The documents date from 1955 to 1976 with the bulk being from 1968 to 1976.
Arrangement
Organized into 4 series: Articles and Papers, Congressional Transcripts and Related Materials, Bibliographic Materials, and Ephemera.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Martin K. Gordon, July 7, 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Removed goverment documents
The following items were removed from the collection because they are available electronically.
Subversive Influences in Riots, Looting and Buring, Hearings Before the Committee on Un-American Activities, House of Representatives, 90th Congress, First Session, Parts: 2, 3 (Los Angeles--Watts),3-A (Los Angeles--Watts) [Corrected Print], 4 (Newark NJ), 6 (San Francisco--Berkeley),
Riots, Civil and Criminal Disorders, Hearings Before the Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations of the Committeee on Government Operations United States Senate 90th Congress, Parts: 1,2,3,3A,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13,14,15,16,17,18,19,20,21,22,23,24, 25
Riots, Civil and Criminal Disorders, College Campus Disorders, Second Interim Report of the Committee on the Government Operations United States Senate Made by its Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations Together Additional, Individual and Minority Views Subersive Involvement in Disruption of 1968 Democratic Party National Convention, Hearings Before the Committee on Un-American Activities, House of Representatives, 90th Congress, Second Session, Parts: 1,2,3
Campus Unrest, Hearings Before the Special Subcommittee on Education of teh Committee on Education and Labor House of Representatives, 91st Congress, First Session on problems of Higher Education, Including Those Relating to Student Financial Assistance, articularly in Regard to the Eligibility rovision of Section 504 of the Higher Education Amendment of 1968
Departments of State, Justice, and Commerce, the Judiciary, and Related Agencies Apropriations for 1970, Hearings Before a Subcommittee of the Committee on Appropriations House of Representatives, 91st Congress, First Session, Part: 1
Investigation of Students for a Democratic Society, Hearings Before the Committee on Internal Security, House of Represntatives, 91st Congress, first session, Parts: 1-A (Georgetown University), 1-B (Georgetown University), 2 (Kent State University), 4 (The American University), 5 (University of Chicago; Communist Party Efforts With Regard to SDS), 6-A (Columbus, Ohio, High Schools), 6-B (Akron, Ohio; Detroit, Mich.; and Pittsburgh, Pa.), 7-A (Return of Prisoners of War, and Data Concerning Camera News, Inc., "Newsreel"), 7-B (SDS Activities at Fort Dix, N.J.; Washington D.C.; and Chicago, Ill.)
Extent of Subversion in Campus Disorders: Hearings Before the Subcommittee to Invesigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate, 91st Congress, First session, Parts: 1 (Testimony of Ernesto E. Blanco), 2 (Testimony of Max Phillip Friedman)
Extent of Subversion in the "New Left", Hearings Before the Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate 91st Congress, second session, Part:1 (Testimony of Robert J. Thoms),2 (Testimony of Ccil M. Pharris, San Francisco Police Department), 3 (Testimony of Marjorie King and Mike Soto), 4 (Testimony of Charles Siragusa and Ronald L. Brooks), 5 (Fall River, Mass.), 6 (Testimony of James W. Rutherford, Louis Szabo, and Charles H. Gilmore), 7 (Testimony of Hugh Patrick Feely and Harry F. Port, Jr.), 8 (Testimony of Clifford A. Murray and Richard M. Schave), 9 (Tesimony of Allen Crouter and Paul Chambers)
Hearings (With subsequent staff interviews) Before the Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on the Judiciary, United State Senate 91st Congress, Second Session, Part:1 (Statements of Robert F. Williams), 2 (Statements of Robert F. Williams), 3 (Statements of Robert F. Williams)
Black Panther Party, Hearings Before the Committee on the Internal Security House of Representatives, 91st Congress, Second Session, Part: 1 (Investigation of Kansas City Chapter; National Organization Data), 2 (Investigation of Seattle Chapter), 3 (Investigation of Activities in Detroit, Mich.; Philadelphia, Pa; and Indianapolis, Ind.), 4 (National Office Operations and Investigation of Activities in Des Moines, Iowa, and Omaha, Nebr.),
Committee on Internal Security, Annual Report for the Year 1969, 91st Congress, first session
Committee on Internal Security, Annual Report for the Year 1970, 91st Congress, second session
Committee on Internal Security, Anual Report for the year 1971 (Together with Supplemental Views and Minoriy View), 92nd, first session
New Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam, Hearings Before the Committee on Internal Security House of Representatives, 91st Congress, Second session, Part: 2
Assaults on Law Envorcement Officers: Hearings Before the Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate, 91st Congress, Second Session, Part: 1 (S. 4325, S. 4348, S. 4359, S.4403), 2 (S. 4325, S. 4348, S. 4359, S.4403), 3 (S. 4325, S. 4348, S. 4359, S.4403), 4 (S. 4325, S. 4348, S. 4359, S.4403), 5 (S. 4325, S. 4348, S. 4359, S.4403)
Hearings Before the Committee on Internal Security House of Representatives 92nd Congress, first session: Progressive Labor Party
Hearings Before the Committee on Internal Security House of Representatives 92nd Congress, first session: National Peace Action Coalition (NPAC), and Peoples Coalition for Peace & Justice (PCPJ), Part: 1,2,3, 4
Hearings Before the Select Committee on Crime House of Representatives, 92nd Congress, First Session, American Prisons in Turmoil, Part:1
Hearings Before and Special Report Made By committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives on Subjects Affecting the Navel and Military Establishments 1972, 92nd Congress, Second Session, books: 2 of 4, 3 of 4, 4 of 4 (and index?)
Revolutionary Activities Directed Toward the Administration of Penal or Correctional Systems, Hearings Before the Committee on Internal Security House of Representatives, 93ed Congress, First Session, Part: 2, 3
Attempt to Steal the Bicentennial The Peoples Bicentennial Commission, Hearings Before the Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate, 94th Congress, Second session
Protest movements; Student movements; Vietnam war; United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on Government Operations. Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations; American Indian Movement; Black Panther Party; People's Coalition for Peace and Justice; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.)
- Articles and papers, 1969-1976; 1969-1970; Series 1; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this series are from periodicals as well as published and unpublished articles by scholars. They date from 1969-1976 with the bulk being from the period 1969-1970. They consist of an academic and journalistic look at the student unrest of the late 1960s and early 1970s. They are organized chronologically and include materials on general as well as specific topics.
  Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); Columbia University
  - The nature of the student movement and radical proposals for changes at Columbia University, 1969; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Columbia crisis: campus Vietnam and the ghetto, 1968; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The faculty role in campus unrest, 1969; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Explanations for student unrest in the US today, 1969; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Student disorders: a study of cultural aims, 1969; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cornell University survey, 1969; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Student strikes, 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General campus unrest, 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - SDS and YAF: a comparison of 2 student radical groups, 1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Status: politics and student politics: an analysis of Left and Right wing student activists, 1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Student protest an institutional and national profile, 1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Student unrest a chronology, 1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commission on campus unrest (Scanton Commission), 1970-1971; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notre Dame magazine "Yesterday's Activists", 1975; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings on Kent State killings, 1970-1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Congressional transcripts and related materials, 1969-1971; 1969-1976; Series 2; 1 Linear Feet
  This series consists of congressional transcripts dating from 1969-1971 and two indicies of publications of the Committee on Un-American Activities from 1938-1968. Most transcripts originally found in this collection have been removed because they are available electronically. Some reports especially those related to the Black Panther Party were retained due to the potentially difficulty in retrieving them from another source.
  United States. Congress. House. Committee on the Judiciary; Black Panther Party; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); American Indian Movement
  - Subcommittee on Investigations of the committee on Gov. Operations, staff study of campus riots and disorders Oct. 1967 - May 1969, 06/1969; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Internal Security: investigation of SDS (GW) part 3-A, 07/22/1969; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Internal Security: investigation of SDS (GW) part 3-B, 07/23/1969-07/24/1969; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Internal Security: Black Panther Party its origin and development as reflected in its official weekly newspaper "The Black Panther Black Community News Service", 10/06/1970; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Internal Sercurity: Gun Barrel Politics: The Black Panther Party, 1966-1971, 08/18/1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Internal Security: Anatomy of a revolutionary movement "Students for a Democratic Society", 10/06/1970; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - List from Library of Congress Congressional Research Service, 1970; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bibliographic materials notes and drafts, 1969-1970; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The "People's Park: A report on a confrontation at Berkley CA by the Office of the Governor, 1969; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Testimony befor the President's Commission on campus unrest, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Survey, press release and Congressional Register, 1970; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cumulative index to the publications of the Committee on Un-American Activities 1938-1954, 08/1962; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Supplement to cumulative index to publications of the Committee on Un-American Activities 1955 through 1968, 09/1970; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Subcommittee to investigate the administation of the Internal Security Act and other internal security laws of the Committee of the Judiciary: Revolutionary activities within the U.S.; American Indian Movement, 09/1976; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subcomittee to investigate the administration of the Internal Security Act and other internal security laws of the Committee on the Judiciary threats to the peaceful observance of the Bicentennial, 06/18/1976; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Bibliographic materials, 1967-1970; Series 3; 0.15 Linear Feet
  This series contain the various list of sources related to campus and community unrest that Gordon collected between 1967 and 1970.
  - Published materials [1/2], 1967-1970; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Published materials [2/2], 1967-1970; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Ephemera, 1970-1971; Series 4; 0.1 Linear Feet
  This series consists primarily of drafts of letters and memorandum from 1970 and 1971 regarding Gordon's work.
  - Ephemera, 1970-1971; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 2)